# Maxime C. Cohen

Last update: January 2020

Email: <a href="maxccohen@gmail.com">maxccohen@gmail.com</a>
Website: <a href="maxccohen.com">http://www.maximecohen.com</a>

My core expertise lies at the intersection of **data science** and **operations management**. I have worked on retail, ride-sharing, airline, sustainability, cloud computing, online advertising, peer-to-peer lending, and social networks. I have collaborated with different companies including Google, Oracle Retail, IBM Research, Via (ride-sharing), Spotify, Cargo, Staples as well as several startups.

# **Employment History**

| Employme                | nt History   |
|-------------------------|--|
| 2019 –                  | <ul> <li>McGill University, BSRM and Desautels Faculty of Management, Montreal, Canada Associate Professor of Retail Management and Operations Management (with tenure)</li> <li>Bensadoun Faculty Scholar</li> <li>Co-director of the McGill Retail Innovation Lab</li> <li>Member of CIRRELT - Research Center on Enterprise Networks, Logistics and Transportation</li> </ul> |
| 2016 – 2019             | New York University, Stern School of Business, New York, NY<br>Assistant Professor of Technology, Operations, and Statistics   |
| 2015 – 2016             | Google AI, Research Team, New York, NY<br>Postdoctoral Research Scientist  |
| 2017 –                  | Cherre, ReBloc.io, Silverback.ai, U.S. and Israel<br>Member of Advisory Board  |
| 2017 –                  | Sarona Ventures, Tel Aviv, Israel<br>Advisor   |
| 2012<br>(Summer)        | <b>IBM T. J. Watson Research Center,</b> Yorktown Heights, NY Research Intern - Business Analytics and Math Sciences   |
| 2012 & 2013<br>(Winter) | <b>Oracle Corporation,</b> Burlington, MA<br>Research Scientist Intern - Retail Global Business Unit   |
| 2009                    | Matrix ABC Capital Markets Ltd (merged into GHF group), Israel<br>High-Frequency Trader  |
| 2007 – 2011             | Eurolaxo Ltd, Israel<br>Co-Founder and Partner - Real Estate Investment Company  |
| Education               |  |
| 2010 – 2015             | MIT, Cambridge, MA Ph.D. in Operations Research - Operations Management Track - GPA: 5/5 Thesis: Pricing for Retail, Social Networks, and Green Technologies   |
| 2006 – 2009             | <b>Technion,</b> Haifa, Israel<br>M.S. in Electrical Engineering - GPA: 96/100<br><b>Thesis:</b> Network Time Synchronization Using Decentralized Kalman Filtering   |
| 2002 – 2006             | <b>Technion</b> , Haifa, Israel<br>B.S. in Aerospace Engineering, Summa Cum Laude - GPA: 93.5/100 (top 2%)<br>Courses in the EE Department - GPA: 98.1/100   |

# Published and Accepted Papers

- 1. M. C. Cohen, R. Lobel, G. Perakis, "The Impact of Demand Uncertainty on Consumer Subsidies for Green Technology Adoption," **Management Science** 62(5):1235-1258, 2016
- 2. M. C. Cohen, Z. Leung, K. Panchamgam, G. Perakis, A. Smith, "The Impact of Linear Optimization on Promotion Planning," **Operations Research** 65(2):446-468, 2017
- 3. L. Baardman, M. C. Cohen, K. Panchamgam, G. Perakis, D. Segev, "Scheduling Promotion Vehicles to Boost Profits," **Management Science** 65(1):50-70, 2019
- 4. J. Chemama, M. C. Cohen, R. Lobel, G. Perakis, "Consumer Subsidies with a Strategic Supplier: Commitment vs. Flexibility," **Management Science** 65(2):681-713, 2019
- 5. M. C. Cohen, "Big Data and Service Operations," **Production and Operations Management** 27(9):1709-1723, 2018
- 6. M. C. Cohen, R. Lobel, G. Perakis, "Dynamic Pricing Through Data Sampling," **Production and Operations Management** 27(6):1074-1088, 2018
- M. C. Cohen, P. Keller, V. Mirrokni, M. Zadimoghaddam, "Overcommitment in Cloud Services Bin packing with Chance Constraints," Management Science 65(7):3255-3271, 2019 and accepted to the 2017 ACM SIGMETRICS Conference
- 8. M. C. Cohen, P. Harsha, "Designing Price Incentives in a Network with Social Interactions," Forthcoming in Manufacturing & Service Operations Management
- 9. M. C. Cohen, C. D. Guetta, K. Jiao, F. Provost, "Data-Driven Investment Strategies for Peer-to-Peer Lending," **Big Data** 6(3):191-213, 2018
- 10. M. C. Cohen, I. Lobel, R. Paes Leme, "Feature-Based Dynamic Pricing," Forthcoming in **Management Science** and accepted to the 2016 ACM Conference on Economics & Computation (EC)
- 11. M. C. Cohen, G. Perakis, R. Pindyck, "A Simple Rule for Pricing with Limited Knowledge of Demand," Forthcoming in **Management Science** and accepted to the 2016 ACM Conference on Economics & Computation (EC)

# **Under Review and Working Papers**

- M. C. Cohen, J. J. Kalas, G. Perakis, "Optimizing Promotions for Multiple Items in Supermarkets," Minor Revision in **Management Science**
- M. C. Cohen, M. D. Fiszer, B. J. Kim, "Frustration-Based Promotions: Field Experiments in Ride-Sharing," Major Revision in **Management Science**
- M. C. Cohen, K. Jiao, "The Impact of IPOs on Peer-to-Peer Lending Platforms," Major Revision in **Management Science**
- M. C. Cohen, S. Gupta, J. J. Kalas, G. Perakis, "An Efficient Algorithm for Dynamic Pricing Using a Graphical Representation," Major Revision in **Production and Operations Management**
- M. C. Cohen, G. Perakis, C. Thraves, "Consumer Surplus Under Demand Uncertainty," Major Revision in **Production and Operations Management**

- M. C. Cohen, M. D. Fiszer, A. Ratzon, R. Sasson, "Incentivizing Commuters to Carpool: A Large Field Experiment with Waze," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, A. N. Elmachtoub and X. Lei, "Pricing with Fairness," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, C. Fernandez, A. Ghose, "Empirical Analysis of Referrals in Ride-Sharing," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, R. Zhang, "Competition and Coopetition for Two-Sided Platforms," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, A. Jacquillat, J. C. Serpa, "A Field Experiment on Airline Lead-in Fares," submitted
- G. Allon, M. C. Cohen, W. P. Sinchaisri, "The Impact of Behavioral and Economic Drivers on Gig Economy Workers," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, K. Jiao, R. Zhang, "Data Aggregation and Demand Prediction," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, A. Desir, N. Korula, B. Sivan, "Best of Both Worlds Ad Contracts: Guaranteed Allocation and Price with Programmatic Efficiency," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, G. Perakis, C. Thraves, "Competition and Externalities in Green Technology Adoption," working paper

## Book Chapter, Practitioner, and Conference Publications

- M. C. Cohen, G. Perakis, "Promotion Optimization in Retail," Channel Strategies and Marketing Mix in a Connected World, (Eds.) Saibal Ray and Shuya Yin, Springer, Forthcoming
- L. Baardman, M. C. Cohen, K. Panchamgam, G. Perakis, "Upgrading Promotions Using Business Analytics," Forthcoming in **Management and Business Review**
- M. C. Cohen, Samuel Dahan, Colin Rule "Conflict Analytics: When Data Science Meets Dispute Resolution," submitted
- M. C. Cohen, I. Lobel, R. Paes Leme, "Ellipsoids for Contextual Dynamic Pricing," SIGecom Exchanges, vol. 15, no. 2, pp. 40-44, 2017
- M. C. Cohen, N. Shimkin, "Decentralized algorithms for sequential network time synchronization," Proc. NETCOOP 2010 4<sup>th</sup> Workshop on Network Control and Optimization, 2010, pp. 97-104

## **Theses**

- M. C. Cohen, "Pricing for Retail, Social Networks and Green Technologies," Ph.D. Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2015
- M. C. Cohen, "Network Time Synchronization Using Decentralized Kalman Filtering," M.S. Thesis, Technion, 2009

## Case Studies

- M. C. Cohen, C. D. Guetta, W. Xiao, "Supply Chain Coordination and Contracts in the Sharing Economy a Case Study at Cargo," Columbia CaseWorks 180203, 2018. Available via Harvard Business Publishing
- M. C. Cohen, G. Perakis, "Optimizing Promotions for Supermarkets Using Data Analytics," Published at thecasecentre.org, 2017

M. C. Cohen, W. Xiao, "Managing Champagne Inventory in a Liquor Store"

M. C. Cohen, C. D. Guetta, M. Reed, "Modern Retail Analytics: Data Visualization using Tableau"

#### **Patents**

US20150081393 A1 – "Product Promotion Optimization System"

Published in March 2015 (M. C. Cohen, Z. Leung, K. Panchamgam, G. Perakis)

**US20150006267 A1** – "Designing Price Incentives in a Network with Social Interactions"

Published in January 2015 (M. C. Cohen, P. Harsha, M. Ettl)

US20130275183 A1 – "Time-Dependent Product Pricing Optimizer"

Published in October 2013 (M. C. Cohen, K. Panchamgam, A. Vakhutinsky)

**US20170140414 A1** – "Computerized Promotion Price Scheduling Utilizing Multiple Product Demand Model" - Published in May 2017 (M. C. Cohen, J. J. Kalas, K. Panchamgam, G. Perakis)

# Teaching Experience

| 2020        | McGill University, Montreal, Canada<br>Operations Management undergraduate core course (2 sections of 65 students)  |
|-------------|---|
| 2020        | McGill University, Montreal, Canada<br>Revenue Management elective course for Master of Management in Analytics   |
| 2020        | McGill University, Montreal, Canada<br>Service Analytics elective course for Master of Management in Analytics  |
| 2017 – 2019 | <b>NYU Stern,</b> New York, NY Operations Management undergraduate core course (2 sections of 70 students each year). Evaluations: 6.6, 6.7, 6.5, 6.7 (out of 7), 4.8, 4.8 (out of 5) |
| 2019        | <b>NYU Stern,</b> New York, NY Operations in the Sharing Economy (doctoral course). Evaluation: 5/5   |
| 2016        | NYU Stern, New York, NY<br>Lecturer for "Applying Revenue Management: Optimization in Retail" – M.S. in Business<br>Analytics program - 61 students                                   |
| 2013 & 2014 | MIT, Cambridge, MA<br>Instructor for "Data, Models and Decisions: Pre-Term" – MBA refresher - 93 students   |
| 2012 – 2013 | MIT, Cambridge, MA TA for "Introduction to Operations Management" – Elective/core MBA course TA for "Introduction to Healthcare Delivery" – Elective MBA and Ph.D. course             |
| 2006 – 2009 | <b>Technion,</b> Haifa, Israel<br>TA for Random Signals, Control Systems, and Non-Linear Control Systems  |

## Students

Baek Jung Kim (2019) - Marketing Ph.D. student at NYU (advisors: M. Ishihara and V. Singh). First position: Assistant Professor of Marketing, UBC Sauder School of Business

Kevin Jiao (2019) - OM Ph.D. student at NYU. First position: FINRA, Data Scientist

Dmitry Mitrofanov (2020) - OM Ph.D. student at NYU (advisor: Srikanth Jagabathula). First position:

Assistant Professor of Operations Management, Boston College Carroll School of Management

Haotian Song - OM Ph.D. student at NYU (advisor: Wenqiang Xiao)

Park Sinchaisri - OID Ph.D. student at Wharton (advisor: Gad Allon)

Xiao Lei - IEOR Ph.D. student at Columbia University (advisor: Adam Elmachtoub)

Carlos Fernandez - IS Ph.D. student at NYU (advisor: Foster Provost)

Weitao Lin (2018) - M.S. in Data Science at NYU. First Position: RBC Capital Markets, Data Scientist

Marcos Galante (2018) - NYU UG Stern Honors. First Position: Goldman Sachs, Investment Banking

Junge Zhang (2020) - M.S. in Data Science at NYU

Matthieu Reed (2020) - McGill UG Integrated Management Student Fellow

## Professional Service

Associate editor for M&SOM Special Issue on Smart City Operations (2019-2020)

Senior editor for Production and Operations Management (2017-present)

Associate editor for M&SOM Special Issue on Sharing Economy and Marketplaces (2018-2019)

Associate editor for NRL Special Issue on Service Operations (2018-2019)

Advisor for Management and Business Review (2019-present)

Co-founder and co-organizer of NYC Operations Day (2018-2019)

INFORMS Revenue Management and Pricing cluster chair (2019)

Program committee for ACM conference on Economics and Computation (2019)

NYU Stern MSBA Capstone Faculty Adviser (2019-2020)

BSRM hiring committee member at McGill University (2019)

OM faculty recruitment committee member at NYU Stern (2018-2019)

OM seminar coordinator at NYU Stern (2016-2019)

OM Ph.D. program committee member at NYU Stern (2016-2019)

Co-organizer of "Disruptions in the Consumer Experience," BSRM McGill University (2019)

Committee member of the New Frontiers in Research Fund (2019)

Reviewer: Management Science, Operations Research, Manufacturing & Service Operations

Management, Production and Operations Management, The Review of Economics and Statistics, Naval

Research Logistics, Management and Business Review, Networks, MSOM SIG, INFORMS Behavioral OM Best Paper Award

Reviewer for Hong Kong research grants council (2017-2019)

Reviewer for the Canadian Mitacs accelerate research program (2018-2019)

Program committee for the INFORMS Revenue Management and Pricing Conference (2016)

Session chair (INFORMS 2016-2019; POMS 2016, 2018)

Student coordinator for the MIT ORC Seminar series (Spring 2013), Officer at the INFORMS student chapter at MIT (2010-2011)

#### Awards & Grants

2019: First Place in the Best OM Paper in Management Science Award

2019: Finalist in the INFORMS Data Mining Section Best Paper Competition

2019: Finalist in the INFORMS BOM Section Best Working Paper Competition

2019: Best Paper Award in Operations and Supply Chain Management, Academy of Management

2019: Honorable Mention in the ENRE Best Publication Award in Environment and Sustainability

2019: Finalist in the INFORMS Case Competition

2019-2021: Bensadoun Faculty Scholar Award - \$20,000 per year for 3 years

2019: Cherre's Gift for Research Excellence: Applying Data Science to Real Estate - \$10,400, Role: PI

2019-2021: SSHRC New Frontiers Grant: AI-Tribunal for Small Claims: Building an Intelligent Dispute

Resolution System - \$244,562, Role: Co-applicant (with S. Dahan, X. Zhu, J. Serpa, Y. Levin, J. Touboul)

2018: M&SOM Meritorious Service Award

2018: First Place in the Best Cluster Paper Award - INFORMS Service Science

2018: Finalist in the M&SOM Student Paper Competition (student: Baek Jung Kim)

2018: First Place in the INFORMS Case Competition

2018: Best Technical Presentation, AGIFORS Annual Symposium

2017: M&SOM Meritorious Service Award

2017: Honorable mention in the Best Cluster Paper Award - INFORMS Service Science

2016: INFORMS Revenue Management and Pricing Dissertation Award

2016: First Place in the Best Cluster Paper Award - INFORMS Service Science

2015: Finalist in the INFORMS Revenue Management and Pricing Practice Award

2015: First Place in the Best Student Paper POM Supply Chain

2015: NEDSI Conference Best Application of Theory Award

2014: First Place in the Best Student Paper - INFORMS Service Science

2014-2015: UPS Ph.D. Fellowship (awarded to a single MIT Ph.D. student)

2013-2014: Martin's Fellowship for Sustainability

2011-2012: MIT Energy Initiative Fellowship

2006-2008: Technion Excellence scholarship and Lady Davis Fellowship

2007: Winner of the Technion Creativity in Science and Technology competition

2007: Best student project of the 47th Israel Annual Conference on Aerospace Sciences

2002-2006: Technion Presidential and Dean Honors

#### Seminars and Research Presentations

**2020:** HEC Montreal (scheduled), CIRRELT (scheduled), University of Toronto OM Seminar (scheduled)

2019: Cornell Tech, Google Product Analytics, POMS Conference, Triennial Invitational Choice Symposium, INFORMS Annual Meeting, Microsoft Research Economics Seminar, Conflict Analytics Queens Law Seminar, Queen's University OM Seminar, DTL Quebec Retail Council of Canada, McGill Decision Neuroscience Seminar

<u>2018:</u> NYU OM Seminar, OMEGA Baruch College Seminar, Via Growth and Data Science Meeting, NYU IS Seminar, Fashion Retail Conference, Technion IE&M Seminar, Marketplace Innovation Workshop, RMP Conference, MSOM Service SIG and MSOM Conference, MIT OM Seminar, McGill Retail Seminar, UT Austin McCombs, Spotify Research and ML Seminar, INFORMS Annual Meeting

**2017:** University of Maryland, NYU OM Seminar, MSOM Conference, ACM SIGMETRICS, INFORMS Annual Meeting

<u>2016:</u> Google Cloud Analytics Seminar, RMP Conference, NYU Stern IOMS Colloquium, POMS Conference, Google Algorithms Seminar, ACM Conference on Economics and Computation, INFORMS Annual Meeting

<u>2015</u>: Cornell Johnson, Cornell ORIE, Duke Fuqua, UNC Chapel Hill, UT Dallas, Chicago Booth, NYU Stern, Boston College, Harvard Business School, Michigan Ross, Berkeley Haas, Stanford GSB, Yale SOM,

Columbia DRO, CMU Tepper, UCLA Anderson, INSEAD, Cornell Tech, Google NYC, McGill, RMP Conference, NEDSI, MSOM Conference, ISMP, POMS Conference, INFORMS Annual Meeting

**2014:** Technion IE&M Seminar, UBC Sauder, Northwestern Kellogg, Cornell Big Data Workshop, MSOM Conference, Oracle Retail Seminar, MIT Sloan OM Seminar, INFORMS Annual Meeting

2013: MSOM Conference, INFORMS Annual Meeting

**2012:** ISMP, Optimization Seminar IBM Watson Research Center, MSOM Conference, POMS Conference, INFORMS Annual Meeting

**2011:** MIT Sloan OM Seminar, IBM Student Workshop on Smarter Cities, MIT Energy Research Conference, POMS Conference, INFORMS Annual Meeting

# Languages, Computer Skills, and Personal

Languages: French (native), English (fluent), Hebrew (fluent)

Programming languages: R, Python, MATLAB, C/C++, Maple, Gurobi/CPLEX/Julia, Tableau

Extracurricular activities: hiking, travelling, and sports: squash, soccer, tennis